<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity of adhering to the Church of England as by law established, or, The duty of a good Christian, and particularly parents and masters of families under the present toleration by William Saywell ...</title>
            <author>Saywell, William, 1643-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19475781</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19475781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108859</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62281)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108859)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1677:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity of adhering to the Church of England as by law established, or, The duty of a good Christian, and particularly parents and masters of families under the present toleration by William Saywell ...</title>
                  <author>Saywell, William, 1643-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Hayes ..., for Edw. Hall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge (England) :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108859:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITY Of Adhering To the Church of ENGLAND As by Law eſtabliſhed: OR The Duty of a Good Chriſtian, And particularly of PARENTS and MASTERS OF FAMILIES UNDER The Preſent Toleration.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Saywell,</hi> D. D. Arch-deacon of <hi>Ely.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Theſe are they who ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Hayes</hi> Printer to the Univerſity; for <hi>Edw. Hall</hi> Bookſeller there. 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:108859:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. 23. 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Gabr. Quadring, <hi>Procan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Jo. Beaumont.</item>
                     <item>Humf. Gower.</item>
                     <item>Joh. Covel.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:108859:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO All in any Authority, ESPECIALLY To Parents and Maſters of Families, IN THE ARCH-DEACONRY Of <hi>ELY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have in the following Diſcourſe ſhewed you the true way to Peace and Happineſs upon Earth, and the certain means of Salvation in the World to come, if you will keep your ſelves and Families in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and practiſe thoſe Rules and Orders which She has required for your Publick Devotion and duties of Religion. And alſo made it evident what danger your Children and Servants are in of being ruined, if you doe not make uſe of that Power and Authority which God has given you over them, to ſee them duely Inſtructed in their Catechiſm, and brought up in a Religious converſation, and conſtant attendance at the Prayers and Sacraments of the Church. This I have often urged with great earneſtneſs to your Miniſters and Church-wardens, as they can very well teſtifie; and this if I had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity,
<pb facs="tcp:108859:3"/>I ſhould deliver to your conſideration in your ſeveral Pariſhes, and I doubt not, but your Miniſters often put you in mind of the ſame; but my ſtrength and other occaſions not affording me leaſure to do that, I do ſend theſe Books, which you may Read and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate upon at your ſpare times: And for your farther direction, beſides your Bible and Common-Prayer, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to Your and Their ſerious peruſal, a Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The whole Duty of Man,</hi> where you have So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Pious diſcourſes about your particular Duties, and alſo uſefull directions about Prayer and other parts of Private Devotion. 'Tis not only Meat and Drink you are to take care of for your Families, as the Beaſts do for their young; but you are alſo to provide for their Souls which are the better part, and therefore ſee them educated in the true Faith, and Obedience to God, and made uſefull Inſtruments to promote the Peace and welfare of their Country. Schiſm and Hereſie will make them enemies to both, and to you to: It will teach them to be ſtubborn and ſelf-willed, Proud and Moroſe, Peeviſh and ill Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Falſe and Treacherous, and common diſturbers of the Church and State; all which inconveniences you will avoid if you bring them up in the conſtant Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for She only here teaches them the true old Way, and the plain Doctrines of the Catholick Church, and She is the only particular Church to whom by the Laws of God and Man you are bound to yield ſubmiſſion; and this has been fully made out not only againſt Papiſts, but all other Schiſmaticks and Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>This all Godfathers and Godmothers ought to take into their ſerious Conſideration, and where Parents are careleſs or erroneous, they ſhould uſe their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb facs="tcp:108859:3"/>to ſee their God-ſons and God-daughters brought up in the Profeſſion of that Faith into which they were Baptized: the neglect whereof, has made the command of the Church herein ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained off and condemned by the Diſſenters, for elſe no Man in his wits can find fault with the Churches care in this matter. Since beſide the Parents, (who have a natural Obligation to breed up their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fear of God) others are engaged to take care to ſee that done in Caſe the Parents dye or neglect it. Indeed it is every Chriſtians care in ſome meaſure, but that it might be more Orderly managed, 'tis layd upon ſome few to take it into their more eſpecial Charge, and uſually left amongſt Friends and Relations, which in Reaſon and Nature will be moſt carefull to ſee it done. To ſay it is much neglected, is no more then may be ſaid of too many Parents alſo: but the cuſtome is very good, and Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ought to be more carefull to perform the Truſt that the Church and Friends lay upon them, and to do what they can by themſelves or others, is all that is expected.</p>
            <p>But it is not onely teaching them their Catechiſm is ſufficient, but you ought to ſee that they lead their Lives according to thoſe Pious Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections that the Church has taught them, and alſo carefully to reſtrain them, and to correct them for their Vices and Debauchery, ſuch as Swearing, Lying, Drunkenneſs, abſenting from the Church, and all other kind of Wickedneſs: and the better to prevent all theſe miſchiefs, carry them with you at all times to the Church, and take account of them what they have Learned and Obſerved from the Miniſters Sermons and Catechizing, and be oftentimes on Sundays, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:108859:4"/>and other Leaſure times putting them in mind of their Duty.<note place="margin">See Deut. 6.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This the State as well as the Church does now more particularly require of you,<note place="margin">Deut. 11.18.19.</note> during the Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which is not meant to juſtifie Hereſie or Schiſm, or to warrant that they are in a ſafe condition that ſeparate from the Church, no more then <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> who have the like benefit: much leſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Ignorance and Profaneſs, but only to take off the Temporal Puniſhment which the Civil State did inflict. Now God does often defer his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to wait for our amendment, and Parents and Maſters do ſometimes think it convenient to wink at Offences in their Children and Servants; and ſo thô the State does not at preſent puniſh Diſſenters, yet it does ſo far diſapprove of their Wayes, that all the Obligations in Conſcience to Conform to the Church ſtill remain, both by the Laws of the Church and State alſo. Neither is any Man thought fit to be admitted to any Office or Place of Truſt that does not joyn in Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Beſides you muſt conſider, thô Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be an outward means, yet 'tis voluntary Obedience makes good Chriſtians. If therefore you will diſcharge your Duty to God, to the Church and State, and the Obligation you owe to your Families, you muſt diligently obſerve theſe Directions, and take more particular Care at this time in the educating of your Children and Servants in the Communion of the Church, nay if you expect they ſhould receive any Benefit from any Publick employment in Church or State. And I pray God direct you and make you carefull herein; and I as I have opportunity ſhall ſometimes come and ſee, and enquire how well your
<pb facs="tcp:108859:4"/>Pariſh-Churches and Sacraments are frequented by thoſe who would be accounted hearty Friends and true Sons of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> For if they are careleſs herein, how can we expect it from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who would rejoyce at our Deſtruction; and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the end will reap the greateſt advantage by our Diſorders. As you therefore love God, love your Country, love your Childrens Souls, keep them from Conventicles, and be carefull in training them up in the conſtant Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> God does particularly commend <hi>Abraham</hi> becauſe he did <hi>command his Children after him that they ſhould keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18 19.</note> And <hi>Joſhua</hi> does not only take care for himſelf, but ſays, <hi>As for Me and my Houſe we will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 24.15.</note> And it is the Command of God in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Epheſ. 6.4. That you ſhould bring up your Children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord:</hi> And what that is I have here ſet before you, to prevent your falling into the Errours and Confuſions of the times. And how can you better ſpend your Dayes then in promoting the Glory of God, and Peace and Love round about you, and obtaining happineſs for your Selves and Families to all Eternity? God be thanked the Pious Zeal of the Sons of the Church has had ſo good effect in the City of <hi>London,</hi> that daily Morning and Evening Prayers, Weekly and Monthly Communions, are Reverently and Devoutly celebrated and frequented in many Churches and Chappels. I hope their good example will ſtir up People in the Countrey to change their careleſs beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to be reverent and conſtant in doing their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and attending the Prayers and Sacraments of the Church.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:108859:5"/>
               <bibl>Calvin. de neceſſ. Reform. Eccleſ.</bibl>
               <p>LET them give us ſuch an Hierarchy, in which Biſhops have ſuch a preheminency, that they do not refuſe to be ſubject to Chriſt, wherein they depend upon him as their only Head, and are referred unto him; in which let them maintain Brotherly Charity one with another, and be united together with no other Bond than of his Truth: Then I will confeſs there is no <hi>Anathema</hi> that they are not guilty of, if there be any ſuch, that do not obſerve it Reverently and with the higheſt Obedience.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Calv. de vera Reformand. Ration.</bibl>
               <p>That no Man may raiſe a Calumny againſt us, that we are too moroſe and froward concerning external things, and do ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely take away all Liberty; I do here teſtifie that I do not contend about Ceremonies, which ſerve for Order and Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or elſe are Simbols and Incitements of that Reverence which we pay to God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Calv. Ep. 87. Protect. Angl.</bibl>
               <p>I do highly approve that there ſhould be a certain Form of Prayer and Eccleſiaſtical Rites, from which it ſhould not be Lawfull for Paſtors themſelves to diſcede or vary. <hi>1.</hi> That proviſion may be made for ſome Peoples ignorance and unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs. <hi>2.</hi> That the conſent of all Churches amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may more plainly appear. <hi>3.</hi> That Order may be taken againſt the deſultory lightneſs of ſuch who delight in innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thus there ought to be an eſtabliſhed Catechiſm, an eſtabliſhed Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and alſo a Publick Form of Prayer.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108859:5"/>
            <head>THE Neceſsity of adhering TO The Church of ENGLAND as by Law eſtabliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope I have made it evident to you that I have a tender regard for the glory of God and the good of your Souls, by the great pains and the charge I was at to ſend you Books to ſtir you up, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you to the ſerious practice of the duty of Godlineſs; for tis not hearing all the Sermons and melting diſcourſes in the world can bring you to Heaven, unleſs you do truly <hi>Love God, with all your heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Matt. 22.37.</note> 
               <hi>with all your ſoul, with all your mind, and with all your ſtrength;</hi> which is not done by running now and then into a Conventicle, and ſighing and groaning at a paſſionate expreſſion of the Preacher, but by a conſtant and ſteady doing of your Duty. There are in the world many errours in opinion deſtructive of ſalvation, and there are more in practice. But of late years, ſince my coming to this Office, our Churches have been much more filled, and the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper better frequented, and the generality of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108859:6"/>the People ſeemed to be very well ſatisfied with the Doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, and there need nothing but a hearty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the rules and order of it, to make us all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Gods glory here on earth, and happy to all eternity in the kingdom of Heaven. And that I might more effectually perſwade you to live in all Chriſtian obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the will of God, I thought ſome motives to the duty of Godlineſs, with ſhort directions and prayers, would be a means to make you more ready and willing to lead a holy and Religious life This was my real deſign and intention in ſending that little Book amongſt you, which if you would often and carefully read over, and obſerve the directions contained in it, you would and more ſolid comſort and ſatisfaction upon your death bed, or when you come to examine into the hopes you have of Salvation, then in all the paſſionate Sermons that ever you heard in a Conventicle, for then you would do your duty as God hath commanded you; whereas now moſt men content themſelves with hearing only, and that not as they ought to doe neither, and ſo deceive their own ſelves, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22.</p>
            <p>Since the coming abroad of that little Book, when I thought I had little elſe to do but to call upon you to do your duty which you did already own and profeſs, I am how put upon another care by the change of affairs in the State, in order to the faithful diſcharge of my Office, that is to endeavour to recall ſome, and ſecure others in the unity and communion of the Church; now when you are ready to hear every new Man that ſets up in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, and read erroneous books to lead you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, I hope you will read and conſider what your Spiritual Governours (who have as great a concern for your good as They have a blind Zeal for your hurt) have to ſay for the truth, and your obedience to the Laws of the Goſpel. And 'tis from the earneſt deſire I have of your peace and welfare, and the ſalvation of your Souls, that I do now again apply my ſelf to you, and require you as you will anſwer it at the Day of judgement, when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108859:6"/>I muſt give an account how I have done my duty to was do you, ſeriouſly to conſider how you that run into ſchiſm will anſwer this Charge which I now draw up againſt you, when the ſcoffs and jears of your Leaders, the all I urements and threatnings of your companions, and of your friends in errour will ſtand you in no ſtead, but you muſt each ſtand by your ſelves to be Judged at the day of your death according to the word of God, which I now offer to your conſideration.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The pretence of Conſcience and being ſatisfied in their way without aſſurance from the Scriptures is an unſafe foundation.</head>
               <p>I Know it is the temper of many of you to ſay we are ſatisfied, and you feel a great deal of comfort in the way you take to worſhip God, and have the teſtimony of your Conſcience that you do act ſincerely, and as you think, for the glory or God. But how eaſily may Men flatter and deceive themſelves with ſuch pretences? Do not Jews and Mahometans, all Hereticks and Schiſmaticks pretend the ſame? And are not many of them fully as Zealous and conſident in their way, and do they not as much condemn you in their thoughts as you can them? Nay thoſe that killed the Apoſtles thought they did God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? So that to rely upon an inward ſatisfaction,<note place="margin">Joh. 16.2.</note> the pretence of Conſcience, without ſolid reaſon and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Gods word, is the common miſtake that deludes the greateſt part of Mankind. If ever then you hope to appear with comfort before God, you muſt lay aſide fancy and perſwaſion, and examine both your <hi>Faith,</hi> and your <hi>Lives</hi> according to the holy Scriptures. <hi>If we or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from Heaven</hi> preach any <hi>other Gospel</hi> in part or in whole, or neglect any part of This, <hi>let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8. When our Saviour began to preach, this was the Summ of his Doctrine, <hi>Repent and relieve the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108859:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Goſpel,</hi> Mar. 1.15. When he ſent his Apoſtles into the world, it was with this large Commiſſion, <hi>Preach the Goſpel to every Creature, he that believeth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16.15, 16. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards ſpeaking of the Day of Judgment, Says, <hi>God ſhall Judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Goſpel,</hi> Rom. 2.16. Again, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus ſhall he revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Gospel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his power.</hi> The Goſpel does not only contain promiſes but precepts, duties, as well as rewards. And therefore our Saviour when he is asked what a man ſhould do to be ſaved, gives this anſwer, <hi>If thou wilt enter into life keep the Commandments.</hi> Again, <hi>if ye love me keep my Commandments.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>James</hi> ſays, <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point he is guilty of all,</hi> Jam. 2.10. This contains all articles of our Creed, and all other Chriſtian duties, we muſt not think then our Zeal for one duty, will excuſe our neglect of another, we muſt not ſo much regard what we have done, but ſupply that we have not done. If through errour or miſtake, any have lived in Schiſm, Hereſie, Diſobedience, or breach of any other command, he muſt repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, for no confidence and ſelf conceit can juſtifie us before God, while we live in neglect of our Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Obedience to Governours and love and unity with our fellow Chriſtians, neceſſary Duties of the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>AS our Saviour came into the World to reform the errours and vices of corrupt Nature, and teach Men the principles of Peace and Vertue, ſo in his Goſpel he has given moſt ſevere commands of mutual love and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Biſhops and Governours, becauſe without it there would be nothing but ignorance and errour, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108859:7"/>and confuſion, and as it was in the Jewiſh Nation when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every one did what was right in his own eyes, ſo it will be in the Church where there are no Governours, or none that are hearkened to or regarded, every man will follow the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of his own heart. Therefore when he founded his Church, the firſt thing he does is to appoint Governours with power not only to ſhut out of his Church, but out of Heaven, all thoſe that contemn their authority and will not be governed by them. Matt. 16.18, 19. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this rock will I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it, and I will give unto thee the keys of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth ſhalt be bound in Heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> And though in this place it be promiſed to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſhew that each ſingle Biſhop had that power in his reſpective charge whilſt he lives in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with and conformity to the Church, yet <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. it is ſaid, <hi>whatſoever ye ſhall bind on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven;</hi> and when our Saviour actually beſtows this power, <hi>John</hi> 20.23. he gives it equally to all the Apoſtles, <hi>whoſe ſoever ſins ye remit, they are remitted, and whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain they are retained.</hi> Again he ſays, <hi>he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth you receiveth me, he that rejecteth you rejecteth me, and he that rejecteth me, rejecteth him that ſent me.</hi> And when he was going into Heaven, that he might fully provide for the order and government of his Church, he gives his Apoſtles authority over the whole World, to rule and to puniſh them, as well as to teach and comfort them; and this power is to laſt to the end of the World. <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and Earth, go ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into all the World, make Diſciples all Nations, and lo I am with you alwayes unto the end of the World,</hi> Matt. 28. The Apoſtle <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. bids Chriſtians <hi>remember them that have the Rule over you, who have spoken to you the word of God, whoſe faith follow,</hi> v. 7. again, <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls,</hi> v. 17. And 'tis our Saviours expreſs command, <hi>if he refuſe to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as a Heathen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108859:8"/>and a Publican,</hi> and then he adds, to ſhew whom he means by the Church, that 'tis the Biſhops and Governours of his Church, <hi>whatſoever ye ſhall bind on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven,</hi> Matt. 18.17, 18. So that it is beyond all poſſible doubt that there are Biſhops and Governours ſent by Chriſt to continue to the end of the World, and there is a Church that muſt be hearkened unto, under peril of being ſhut out of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>There muſt be a method and order obſerved in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the Biſhops and Governours of the Church, that Men may know whom they ought to obey, and whoſe puniſhments they ought to avoid.</head>
               <p>ALL Men confeſs in general, that Chriſt has left Biſhops and Governours in his Church, but they are not all agreed who are thoſe who have this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty committed to them: Now there muſt be ſome orderly method for our direction in this as well as other matters, or elſe the Authority will ſignifie nothing, and not attain that end for which it was appointed. For if every body be left to follow whom he pleaſe, then all cenſures and excommunications will come to nothing, aſſoon as Men are ſhut out from one Paſtor, they will run to another; if one will not comply with their humour, they will go to another that will, and ſo the Chriſtian ſociety, which ought to be the Pattern of order and unity, will be the moſt confuſed body in the World; every body will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his own Lord and Maſter, and will live and do as he lift, but how oppoſite is this to that command of our Saviour? <hi>If he refuſe to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen man and a Publican,</hi> and to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>obey them that have the Rule over you:</hi> when at this rate no Man has any other Ruler but his own peeviſh will.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour therefore to prevent this confuſion, as he had Authority immediatly from God, ſo he gave his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108859:8"/>full Commiſſion to ſend others with the like power of appointing new Biſhops to the end of the World, as faſt as any ſhould dye or the places become void. And to this purpoſe he ſays, <hi>as my Father ſent me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 20.</note> that is with power of ſending you, <hi>ſo ſend I you,</hi> with power of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others. <hi>And lo, I am with you alwaies unto the end of the World;</hi> accordingly we find <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the appointment of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3. and they again when they had received this power goe about ordaining Biſhops in every Church where they were wanting, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. and then <hi>Acts</hi> 20. the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts the Biſhops to <hi>feed the Flock of Chriſt over whom the Holy Ghoſt had made them Biſhops.</hi> Thus <hi>Timothy</hi> was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> and he had power to ordain others, but he is charged to <hi>lay hands ſuddenly on no Man,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. <hi>Titas</hi> alſo was left in <hi>Crete to ordain Elders and ſet in order the things that were wanting.</hi> So that Chriſt he firſt ſent forth his Apoſtles, the Apoſtles they ordained and ſent forth Biſhops, they were to judge of their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and ſo to give them charge of Souls, and the People were to hearken to them and obey them as appointed by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. and ſo other Prieſts and Officers that follow their orders and directions, 2 Cor. 7.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What method was obſerved in appointing Biſhops and Governours of the Church after the Apoſtles dayes.</head>
               <p>'TIS not to be expected that the Names of all the Perſons that were called to be Governours in the Church, and the places and bounds within which every Man was to exerciſe his Authority, ſhould be ſet down in Scripture, no more then the Names and Places of Kings and Printes and Civil Governours are. The common rules of prudence and order are enough to direct in this as well as the other matters, ſo that all things be done <hi>decently and in order,</hi> and to the <hi>edification of the Church.</hi> Now the Rules of decency and order do require that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108859:9"/>Perſons ſhould be appointed peaceably, and therefore no Man muſt thruſt himſelf into any Government till he be duely called and ſet apart for that Office, neither muſt any one uſurp anothers place and diſturb him in the quiet diſcharge of his duty. And then that all may be done to edification, tis fit the Perſons ſhould be able and well qualified to do their Office; ſo there muſt be Perſons who have power to appoint, and judgement to examine and diſcern the fitneſs of the Men who are to be called to ſo high a dignity as to be Teachers and Governours of the Church; how they are for life and converſation; that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and People can bear witneſs to, and are allowed to except againſt ill Men. But whether they are ſound in Faith, and indued with knowledge and underſtanding rightly to divide the word of God, and diſcharge their duty, that was ever the Office of the Biſhops to enquire, as alſo to ordain and appoint them, for they <hi>muſt lay hands ſuddenly on no Man,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. but are to <hi>commit this Authority to faithfull Men who are able to teach others alſo,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.2. again, <hi>how ſhall they Preach except they be ſent,</hi> Rom. 10.15. <hi>no Man taketh this honour unto himſelf but he that is called of God as was Aaron,</hi> Heb. 5.4. Now that was after a ſolemn and orderly manner, by Gods appointment he was legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſecrated and ſet apart for that Office, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. ſo were the Apoſtles, ſo were thoſe ſent abroad by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſo Perſons were appointed in all ages of the Church, being firſt examined and tryed, and then Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and ſent forth by the Biſhops according to certain Canons, and the ſame order is obſerved at this day in all Churches that ſtand eſtabliſhed in any ſetled Government. And thô there be a diſpute in ſome places whether Biſhops and Prieſts be of the ſame order, and upon that ſuppoſition that every Prieſt is a Biſhop, and has Originally in him fullneſs of all Authority and Power, ſome do take it upon them to ordain thô meer Presbyters, yet it is upon that principle and ſuppoſition that a Presbyter is equal to a Biſhop, and has Authority from Chriſt to ordain others by virtue of his Office, and ſo ſtill they maintain that Men muſt be examined and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108859:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>by Biſhops in a Regular manner, before they ought to be allowed to take upon them any Office of Preaching and Governing in the Church. And ſuppoſe a Biſhop and Presbyter were one Order, and a Presbyter had equal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority originally to Ordain as well as Biſhops, which in the judgment of moſt Churches they have not; yet what an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable thing is it, to make uſe of a power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was never owned and allowed for 1500 years in the Church, and which does create many doubts and diſputes and great confuſion in the Church, when they may have Ordination from the Biſhops, which all confeſs is ſound and valid, and thereby Men may avoid giving ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to many Churches, and raiſing Scruples in the minds of People at home, which all charity does require good Chriſtians to prevent. Now this Succeſſion of Biſhops down from the Apoſtles time to our dayes,<note place="margin">Luther T. 4. p. 6, 7, 8. <hi>Twenty years after his firſt appearing againſt the errors of the Church of</hi> Rome. The Apoſtles were called by Chriſt himſelf, the Apoſtles afterward called their Diſciples, as <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> Who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward called the Biſhops, the Biſhops cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Succeſſors, and that <hi>Call</hi> continued to our times, and ſhall continue to the end of the World, and 'tis a mediate call, becauſe it is by Men, yet it is Divine; and this is the generall call all over the World after the Apoſtles, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be changed, but highly eſteemed, by reaſon of ſome fanaticall Men which deſpiſe it, and boaſt of another better call, whereby they ſay they are moved by the Spirit to teach. But ſuch impoſtors lye, they are moved by a Spirit indeed, but not by a good but a wicked Spirit—Wherefore we muſt not run into another Man's charge, as the Devil does ſtir up his Miniſters to run where they are not called.</note> has run as clearly and as evidently as the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Kings in <hi>England</hi> ſince <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, ſtill one ſucceeding another, as any died or were removed, by Ordination and orderly appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Charge. But yet farther, to keep peace and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent confuſion, there muſt be ſome Canons or Rules, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain every Man within the bounds of his duty, that one might not diſturb another, or undoe what another had done. Now about chuſing of Biſhops and about excommunicating Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders; Biſhops may vary in their opinion, as it is known they often have done, one may be for this Man, and another for that, and unleſs there be ſome Rule to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by, there will be endleſs Cuarrels and Diſputes; therefore the general Rule of Decency and Order muſt come in here, and we muſt conſider what direction the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108859:10"/>Scripture has given in this Caſe alſo. Now beſides the Rule of common Prudence, that amongſt Governours of all Societies, if they cannot otherwiſe compoſe any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, they muſt ſit down by the Authority of the major part: the Apoſtle tells us. <hi>The Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets, for God is not the Author of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion but of Peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints,</hi> 1. Cor. 14. much more then particular Biſhops and Miniſters ought to be ſubject to the reſt of the Biſhops. Then the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule of our Saviour is, <hi>If he refuſe to hear the Church let him be unto Thee as an Heathen man and a Publican;</hi> not only no longer an Officer, but not ſo much as a member of the Church.</p>
               <p>Now all Biſhops being Governours of the Church, and Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, one as well as another has right to judge in Caſes that concern the peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare thereof, but it is impoſſible they can all meet or be conſulted in ordinary Caſes, and therefore as in the Civil ſtate, for better Order and convenience in adminiſtration of Juſtice or preſerving Peace, the World is divided into Kingdoms, Provinces, Counties, Cities, &amp;c. And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Governours have the certain bounds and limits of their juriſdiction, and every one is to take care of all things within his own charge, and not to intermeddle or thruſt himſelf into another Countrey or Province. So by direction from the Apoſtles, the Biſhops did by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſent ſet out the bounds of every Man's juriſdiction, according to Cities and Provinces; and Civil States have confirmed the ſame in after Ages. Thus S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>James</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Andrew</hi> at <hi>Byzantium</hi> now <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> at <hi>Crete, &amp;c.</hi> And after them other ſingle Perſons did ſucceed in their places, as we ſee it is at this Day, as one Biſhop dyes another is choſen and Ordained to ſucceed in his Office. And as a City with the neighbouring Countries round it did make one Biſhops Dioceſs, ſo ſeveral Cities and their adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Villages, did make one Province under one Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. And all matters that did concern the Church were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108859:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be determined by the mutual conſent of the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and of all or the major part of the Biſhops of each Province, and this was the Order derived from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, confirmed by the general Councils,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Ep. 68. can. A poſt. concil. Nice.</note> and generally obſerved through all Ages of the Church. As for the Authority of Patriarchs, and of late years the uſurpation of the Pope, theſe are all incroachments upon the Church, and ſo are the Aſſemblies of Presbyters without or in oppoſition to their Biſhops, much more (the root of all confuſion) an independencie of every Preacher in each ſingle Congregation, and deviations from the Ancient and Apoſtolical Order.<note place="margin">S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Ep. 55. concil. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican.</hi> can. 28.</note> The ſtanding and generall Law and Tradition was that which beſt ſuits with the rules of Decency and Order, that Chriſtians ſhould not be drawn from their own Country, ſhould not be put to long and tedious journies, but have all Matters ended at home by the Arch-Biſhop and Biſhops of each Province amongſt themſelves, who beſt know the ſtate and condition of the People committed to their charge, and are bound by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt as well as duty, to conſult the peace and welfare of their Dioceſes. 'Tis needleſs to cite the Canons,<note place="margin">See the 6 gen. Councils, and particular Councils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by them.</note> the caſe is known to all Schollars that look into the antient Councils and Hiſtories of the Church. And according to this univerſal Order of the Church, 'tis as eaſie for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to know his own Spiritual Governours, as 'tis his Civil. Every Ones charge is allotted, and all within ſuch bounds and limits belong to the Spiritual Government of the Biſhop of the Dioceſs and his Aſſiſtants, and Miniſter of the Pariſh where he lives; and thus 'tis in all Kingdoms and Countries where the Chriſtian Religion is profeſſed, and this Order and Authority all ſober Divines do own and acknowledge. But ſtill it is with this limitation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they hold the Faith and Unity of the Catholick Church, and keep within the Rules of the Goſpel. For all Biſhops and others are members of Provincial Churches, and muſt be ſubject to the Rules and Order of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; and all Provinces are members of the Catholick Church, and muſt keep the unity of Faith of Chriſts myſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eal body. In rites and ceremonies, and private opinions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108859:11"/>in leſſer matters, particular Churches may differ one from another, and each Province or Nation may conſult and provide that which is beſt for themſelves, but then as to Faith and other neceſſary duties, that muſt be the ſame all over the World, and nothing muſt be done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws of Chriſtian Charity, and that mutual Love that we ought to have for all our Brethren in Chriſt; much leſs ought we to do any thing contrary to that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we owe to our Spiritual Fathers that are ſet over us by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. and to the peace and ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Catholick and our own particular Church or Pariſh. Now I cannot ſee what temptation any rational Man that wiſhes well to the promoting of the glory of God and advancement of true Religion, can have to change this antient Apoſtolical Order of a Synod of Biſhops go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning according to the Rules of the Ancient Church, and with the aſſiſtance of their Presbyters, for a Synod of Presbyters only, according to the late Modell of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> invented at <hi>Geneva.</hi> Or what benefit the People would have by it who muſt ſtill be left to the Miniſter of their own Pariſh; neither would they find themſelves in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but worſe condition. Much leſs ſhould make a Schiſm to inforce and bring in ſuch a novelty and invaſion upon their Spiritual Fathers and Brethren in Chriſt: or elſe to deſtroy all Church Govenment, as the Independants, Anabaptiſts and Quakers do, who ſet up Plow men and Thatchers inſtead of Biſhops and Prieſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>All Perſons in this Nation are bound to joyn in Communion with their Biſhop of the Dioceſs and Miniſter of the Pariſh where they live, and the great ſin of thoſe that neglect this Duty.</head>
               <p>I Have made it evident beyond all doubt that there are Spiritual Governours appointed by Chriſt to continue to the end of the World, and all Chriſtian People muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108859:11"/>be under the Authority and Juriſdiction of ſome or other of thoſe Miniſters; and that by direction of the Apoſtles, and conſtant Law of the generall Councils and tradition of all Chriſtian Churches, and the Rules of Decency and Order, all Countries that own the Chriſtian Religion, are generally divided into Provinces and Dioceſes, &amp;c. for the more peaceable management of all affairs. Things being thus ſettled, all thoſe commands in Scripture that People ought to <hi>bearken to the Church; obey them that have the Rule over them;</hi> beſides all thoſe generall precepts, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother, To know them that are over you in the Lord and admoniſh you, to eſteem them highly for their works ſake, &amp;c.</hi> do oblige all People here in <hi>England</hi> to obey their ſeveral Biſhops, and joyn in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with their reſpective Pariſhes, and thoſe that do obſtinately withdraw themſelves from their obedience, do live in open contempt of Chriſt, and manifeſt viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Holy Goſpel, which does require all Men to maintain Love and Charity eſpecially with their Fathers and Governours, and to keep the peace and unity of the Church. All ſuch Men that wilfully and obſtinately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their Schiſm and diſobedience, are not only ſhut out from the priviledges and benefits of the Goſpel, but bring upon themſelves all the curſes and puniſhments denounced againſt ſuch grievous Sinners, for thoſe that are diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to parents are reckoned up amongſt the moſt heinous Offenders, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. Conſider therefore how you will anſwer it to God in the dreadfull day, that do meerly neglect to joyn in the publick Service and Sacraments, and thereby diſobey your Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and affront that Government which Chriſt has ſet in his Church for your good, and as the means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more his Glory and your Salvation: 'Tis not Man but God that you reject, who gave us this Charge over your Souls, and you do deſpite to the Holy Spirit of grace, from whom we receive our Commiſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:108859:12"/>
               <head>Beſies the guilt of diſobedience and contempl of Chriſts Miniſters, you that aſſemble in Conventicles are guilty of Schiſm; which is a damning Sin, and a root of all confuſion.</head>
               <p>AS nothing is more agreeable to the Nature of God then Love and Unity, ſo nothing is more odious to his moſt Holy being, then Schiſm and Diviſion: for the nature of Love is to unite all things in Peace and Order, but the nature of Schiſm is to bring all things to miſery and confuſion. Whatſoever therefore Schiſmaticks may pretend of Zeal for the glory of God, their advancing Piety, and ſetting up Religion in greater purity, the Scripture calls ſuch courſes the works of the fleſh and pronounces the Perſons that follow them Men of carnal affections.<note place="margin">Rom. 16. Gal. 5.</note> Thoſe therefore that do not only withdraw from the obedience of their Lawfull Governours, but ſet up ſeparate Aſſemblies under colour of purer worſhip, do plainly make a Schiſm in the Church and rend the Body of Chriſt in pieces, and are marked out by the Holy Scrip, tures for the grooteſt enemies of God and true Religion Our Saviour fays he that ſhall be angry with his <hi>brother without a cauſe ſhall be in danger of the Judgment, and he that ſays unto him Rache,</hi> that is empty, vain Fellow, and ſo lighting and bringing his Perſon into contempt, <hi>ſhall be in danger of the Gounoil; but whoſoever ſhall ſay thou fools ſhall be in danger of Hell fire.</hi> Now if it be ſo heinous a crime in the ſight of God, to undervalue our Brother, what is it to deſpiſe our Spiritual Fathers, and contemn their godly commands and admonitions, moreover to tear and divide the Church of Chriſt; and inſtead of Love ſtirr up animoſities and contentions, ſtrife and hatred, as is too to evident, and from thence do genenally follow Maſſacres, Rebellions long and bloudy Wars Murder ſubverſion of Kingdoms and States, deſtruction of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and all the cruelties and miſeries that Mankind are lyable unto. As theſe things are manifeſt by experience, ſo Scripture tells us, <hi>Jude</hi> 18, 19. they ſpring from Schiſm;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108859:12"/>
                  <hi>There ſhall be mockers in the laſt times, who ſhall walk after their own ungodly luſts, theſe be they that ſoparate themſelves, ſenſual having not the Spirit;</hi> whereas none glory more of the Spirit then theſe Separatiſts, whom the Apoſtle charges with carnal and ungodly Luſts. Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Mark thoſe that cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which ye have Learned, and avoid them; for they that are ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt but their own helly, and by good words and fair Speeches deceive the heart of the ſimple.</hi> The Apoſtle purſues the ſame matter, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Lor ye are yet Carnall, for whereas there is among you En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying and Strife, and Diviſions, are ye not Carnal and walk as Men? For while one ſaith I am</hi> Paul, <hi>and another I am</hi> Apollos, <hi>are ye not Carnall?</hi> Again, <hi>Galatians</hi> 5.20. reckoning up the works of the Eleſh that ſhut Men out of Heaven, he ſays, <hi>the worke of the Fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe,</hi> he puts down <hi>Strife, Seaitions,</hi> or Schism and Diviſions, <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and then adds, v. 21. <hi>They that do ſuch things ſhall not in herit the Kingdome of God.</hi> So that as Schiſm is an heinous Sin of its own nature, ſo it proceeds from a carnal mind, and that is the root of all other Evils and Diſorders, <hi>James</hi> 4.1. <hi>From whence come Wars and Fightings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? Come they not hence even of your Luſts, that war in your members?</hi> Luſt breeds Diviſion, and Diviſion breeds War. and War brings all other evils with it, eſpecially civil and homebred Wars, which ſpring from this root of Schiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If none of theſe temporal evils follow upon Schiſm (which God grant they may not) yet Schiſm brings in Hereſie, Ignorance and Prophaneſs.</head>
               <p>DID Men keep to the Rule of Gods word, and follow the interpretation of the Catholick Church, they would be ſecure from all danger of Hereſie, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and profaneſs, and would have a ſure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to lead them into the way of Salvation. For all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108859:13"/>the Schiſms, Hereſies and miſtakes that Men ſall into, come by forſaking the guidance of the Church, and wreſting the Scripture to their own deſtruction, which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> ſays many of the unlearned and unſtable do.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> So that in this caſe; the Scripture may be compared to an Apothecaries ſhop full of all fort of wholeſome Medicines, if rightly applyed with judgement and diſcretion, but ſuch as will prove deadly poyſon, if taken at adventure and misimployed. Now our Saviour has given us the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for our direction, which with much ſtudy and pains, we may underſtand our ſelves for our own benefit and inſtruction: yet becauſe few Men who are engaged in worldly pleaſures and buſineſs, &amp;c. do give themſelves ſo much leiſure as to read through and conſider the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures, ſo as to be able to ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all doubts and ſcruples that cunning Hereticks raiſe to pervert them from the Truth. Therefore Chriſt Jeſus left Paſtors and Teachers, and founded a Church, to continue a conſtant Pillar and Monument, to expound to us all difficult and hard places, and to condemn and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure falſe interpretations, and ſtop the mouths of Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, from ſpreading abroad damnable Hereſies to the ruine of your Souls, and then that her Authority might not be deſpiſed,<note place="margin">Matt. 18.</note> The Scripture ſays, if any one <hi>refuſe to hear the Church, let him be unto Thee as an Heathen man and a Publican.</hi> And for our better encouragement to hearken to her inſtruction, our Lord has promiſed that <hi>the gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it,</hi> Matt. 16. And then to direct the unlearned and unſtable, he has ſet <hi>Paſtors and Teachers for the perfecting of the Saints,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt; till we all come in the unity of Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt; that we may henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſleight of Men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive, &amp;c.</hi> So that we do not take off from the fullneſs and ſufficiency of the Scriptures if rightly expounded and underſtood, but for the ſatisfaction of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108859:13"/>unlearned and unſtable, which are the greateſt part of Mankind, we muſt remember, that God has kept up a Church and conſtant ſucceſſion of Biſhops and Miniſters in an Orderly way, to teach us the true meaning of his Word, and to keep up Diſcipline and Order, and ſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from the Hereſies and falſe Interpretations of Schiſmaticks that lead Men unto errour and deſtruction. While Men therefore keep within the City, they are in no danger of being a prey to the wild Beaſts, but if they run into a Wilderneſs, they may eaſily be deſtroyed by them. While they keep within the Ship they are ſecure from drowning, but if they forſake that, and commit themſelves to the unconſtant Waves, 'tis Ten Thouſand to One if they do not miſcarry. So while Men keep within the Communion of the Church, and follow the guidance of thoſe Paſtors which God has appointed to keep them ſteady, there is no danger of their Salvation; but if they forſake the Church, and run into Conventicles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.11.</note> they go out of Gods way, and ſo out of his protection, and are expoſed to all Hereſie and Confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If their Teachers do not Sin wilfully and lead them into Hereſie, yet they may miſlead them through ignorance and unskilfullneſs.</head>
               <p>WHO can tell how oft he offendeth, nay the Heart above all things is deceitfull; therefore 'tis an eaſie matter for Men that follow the guidance of their own underſtanding, and neglect the command of the Church, to be deluded by the Devil, who often appears as an Angel of Light, and yet is ſtill buſie to ſeek whom he may devour. Neither can they hope for the bleſſing of God, and depend upon the promiſe of his direction, when they go into by Pathes and purſue their own devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. How many plain things may ſuch preſumptuous Men overlook? how often may they miſunderſtand ſome parts of Gods word which want more care and attention? Beſides.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108859:14"/>who can be ſure that they come with all Languages and other helps to reading them, or take ſuch pains to read and compare all Texts, as not to be ignorant in many duties of great neceſſity to be obſerved? <hi>And if the blind lead the blind, they both fall into the ditch:</hi> And no wonder if People periſh for want of viſion, when they wilfully run away from the inſtruction of the Church, and follow ſuch ignorant guides who had need to be taught the firſt Principles of humility and underſtanding. Thô therefore by good Words and fair Speeches they may deceive the hearts of the Simple, and may gather many excellent expreſſions out of the Holy Scriptures, yet 'tis a great raſhneſs and want of Judgment, for Men to truſt their Souls upon the skill and underſtanding of ſuch private Seducers; who by their ignorance may leave them without that ſufficient inſtruction which is neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Objections and Queſtions againſt Conformity anſwered.</head>
               <p>BUT ſome will Object, that their ſetting up Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in oppoſition to the Biſhops and Miniſters, is no more then what the Biſhops did in oppoſition to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore if they are Schiſmaticks now, the Biſhops were alſo, by Reforming the Church without the Authority of the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I anſwer,</hi> By the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and all other general Councils, and the conſtant Order of the Catholick Church, all Provincial and National Churches have power to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves, and reform any abuſes or errours that have crept into their Communion. And our Biſhops and Clergy did in an Orderly way lay aſide ſeveral errours that are maintained by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Faith and unity of the Catholick Church, and we do alſo particularly blame the Roman Church for breaking the Order and rejecting the Traditions of the Primitive Fathers and general Councils, but do not at all break the Rule of Chriſtian Charity to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108859:14"/>or any other Church in the World; we leave them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and Govern their own Churches, and do but uſe the ſame Liberty over our own Members, which Chriſt has given, and the Church has ever maintained, which we allow them to uſe over thoſe of their own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for they ought to Reform thoſe abuſes as we have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But is there not a plain rent and diviſion made in the Church by this Reformation, and thoſe that were united before in One Communion, are broken into ſeveral parties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That there are and muſt be Hereſies and Schiſms in the Church, we are taught by the Holy Scriptures,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> 
                  <hi>That they which are approved may be made manifeſt.</hi> But we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer for other Men, it is ſufficient we break Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with no body; we pay all Love and friendſhip, and all that communion that one particular Church ought to pay to another, but we do not intermeddle with their private affairs, or diſturb and embroyl their Communion; and if the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Churches that hold with her, would keep the ſame temper that we have and ſtill do, we ſhould quickly ſee an end of all our Diviſions,<note place="margin">Can. 30.</note> for we differ from none but where they <hi>differ from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and depart from the Primitive purity of thoſe Ancient and Apoſtolical Churches from whence they had their beginning.</hi> And as for that Obedience and Conformity which we require of our own Members, it is no other and upon far eaſier Terms, then all Churches do require of thoſe that are under their reſpective Juriſdictions. So that we are neither the cauſe nor party in any Diviſion. Other Churches that break communion with us, deny that Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that One Member of Chriſts Body ought to pay to another; and thoſe of our own Members that run into Conventicles, ſet up Altar againſt Altar, and divide themſelves from our Communion, go againſt the plain word of God, which requires them <hi>to obey them that have the Rule over them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See my Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. and Cath. unity, &amp;c.</note> againſt the conſtant Order of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church and general Councils, and contrary to the Doctrine and Command of all other Churches in the World.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:108859:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But are there no Reaſons then for Men to refuſe the Communion of their particular Church and Biſhop, and muſt every private Chriſtian alwayes comply with their Governours, whatſoever they ſay or do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They muſt obey their particular Church, in all things Lawfull, which are in all things not contrary to the word of God and the Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But who ſhall be Judge in this Caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſenſe of the Catholick Church in Caſes of doubt is to be conſulted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But is it not hard to know where ſhe may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, and how to underſtand her Senſe in any matter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God has promiſed that the way ſhall be ſo plain, <hi>that a wayfaring Man though a Fool ſhall not err therein;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 35.8. 1 Tim. 3.15.</note> and for our direction tells us, the Church is <hi>the Pillar and Ground of Truth.</hi> And thereupon he has commanded us to hear and obey the Church, and there is no doubt it will be an eaſie matter to underſtand what her Senſe is, in all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes needfull for us to know.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But have not Biſhops and Scholars themſelves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſputes about the Church, and about her Senſe in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral points, and how then can People know the Sence of the Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Men of ſome Judgment and little Reading, are willing to deſpiſe that Authority which is above their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, and Men of great Reading and little Judgment, do not know how to reconcile the ſeeming differences in the Church, but if you conſult your Biſhops and Miniſters, they will ſatisfie you concerning the Senſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church in all parts of your duty. For ſince God has made it our duty to hear and obey the Churches, he will order matters ſo that all People that are willing to follow her direction, may be guided by it: for God does not reveal any thing to us that we cannot believe, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any thing which we cannot perform in the manner it is propoſed to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What plain Rule will you give us to go by in this matter, for we would willingly know the Truth and hearken to the Church.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:108859:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt in all Lawfull, and in moſt doubtfull matters, it is your duty to follow the command of your particular Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what muſt I do in things that ſeem to me contrary to the Word of God, when ſuch are commanded by my particular Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſecond Rule then I would give you is, that if you think or are credibly told, you ought not to joyn with your particular Church in this or that Doctrine or practice, before you make a Schiſm, enquire of learned Men what was the Senſe of the Primitive Fathers and generall Councils, and what is the generall opinion of other Churches, and moſt learned Divines about it, and be ſure you have good Reaſon and Authority before you depart from your own Church in which you live and were Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> This is the way to put me upon a tedious endleſs work, more then either I, or the Perſons I conſult will be ever able to go through.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, no ſuch matter, the Senſe and Conſent of the Scripture and of the Church is ſo clear in all points of duty that People are concerned to know and practice, and the Controverſies are ſo few when rightly ſtated and underſtood, that want to be decided in Order to your doing your duty, that it will be no hard matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive full ſatisfaction; for they are either ſuch that have been long agoe decided, or the Church is wholly ſilent about them, and there is no evidence of Scripture to oblige you to depart from your particular Church upon that account.</p>
               <p>Now conſider in how many matters all Churches are agreed, and the Controverſies long agoe ſetled.</p>
               <p>Firſt, againſt the <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſeſſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</note> which are long agoe condemned for Hereticks, and the Three Creeds that expound the Catholick Faith,<note place="margin">See my enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the means of a happy union.</note> contrary to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe interpretations, are generally received by all Churches. So likewiſe the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> who deny Infant Bapriſm, are likewiſe condemned by all Churches, and 'tis the conſtant Doctrine of the Catholick Church and all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108859:16"/>Reformed Churches, that to ſeparate from their Lawfull Biſhops upon the account of their requiring of them to joyn in ſtated Forms of Prayer, and for enjoyning decent Ceremonies not contrary to the Word of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to ſet up Altar againſt Altar, and run into private meetings, is that Schiſm condemned in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. So that not only from the Holy Scriptures, but from the interpretation of the Church, it is moſt evident that they hold pernicious if not Damnable errours, and in theſe points it will be an eaſie matter for every body to find ſatisfaction, and to know the Churches Senſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them. So that to joyn with ſuch Diſſenters, and to profeſs their Doctrines, is manifeſtly to oppoſe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as well as the Word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But if you put us to enquire into the Ancient ways, and conſult the Senſe of other Churches, and give us that Rule for our direction in matters of Controverſie; we fear you have a deſign to lead us back to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they talk much of the Church, and the old Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and tell us all the World is on their ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is the great weakneſs of ſome to imagine ſo, and by their ſpeaking meanly of hearkning to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Catholick Church, make many Suſpect indeed that the Church of God has been altogether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and loſt; or elſe no where to be found for many Ages but in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Whereas if you will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of your Biſhops, and Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they will tell you that the pretended Authority of the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is contrary to the generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, rejected by the whole Church for the firſt Six Hundred Years and upwards, and condemned by the major part of the Biſhops and Chriſtian Churches, from the Apoſtles times, to this very day; nay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the only Church by Name warned to take heed leaſt <hi>ſhe be Cut off from the Body of Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. So that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo far from being the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, that ſhe is a very corrupt part of it; and thoſe of that Communion that amongſt us ſet up ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Aſſemblies, do oppoſe the conſtant tradition of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108859:16"/>Catholick Church, the Canons of the generall Councils, and follow a private Spirit, and are as proper Schiſmaticks as any of our <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do not only charge us with Diſobedience to the Pope, but with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and falſe Doctrine, in rejecting many Articles of Faith and other Ancient practices of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if you will conſult your Biſhops and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they will make it appear, that the Points we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject are ſo far from being Articles of Faith, and ancient practices, that they are Moddern errours and corruptions, not known to, or elſe condemned by the Primitive Church, and this we may ſee evidently made out by ſeverall late Writings and Diſputes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> I am glad to hear you ſay the Catholick Church does plainly condemn the Uſurpations and Errours of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as the Scriptures, which ſeem plainly againſt them, and we think againſt many Orders of the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo that are meer Humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, if not old Popiſh Superſtitions, which we cannot Lawfully joyn withall, and therefore are forced to ſerve God in ſuch a Manner as we can, and which we think is better pleaſing to Him, thô in ſeparate Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Humane Inventions, and Popiſh Superſtitions, are frightfull words indeed; but ſo you muſt remember, are Slanderers, Schiſmaticks, Hereticks, and diſobedient to Parents, &amp;c. as all thoſe are that accuſe the Church, and cannot prove what they ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But our Preachers have told us that theſe Orders of the Church are Popiſh, Anti-chriſtian, &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Conſciences would condemn us, if we ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But will you run into ſo great Sins againſt the plain Word of God, becauſe your Preachers tell you ſo. I thought the Word of God had been your Rule, but now I perceive you follow your Preachers againſt the Word of God, and will not obey your Governours according to it.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108859:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> We think our Preachers are Good and Holy Men, and Teach us the Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why ſhould you not have as good an opinion of your Biſhops and Miniſters? But when the Preachers take upon them thus to draw you into Schiſm, Diſobedience, and teach you to have uncharitable thoughts of your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and to condemn the Church and fellow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; you ought to ſuſpect if not their honeſty, yet their Judgment and Diſcretion, for they are Men, and may be tranſported by Paſſion and Intereſt, or elſe through errour and miſtake, and lead you into heinous Sins. For why ſhould you think them wiſer and better then all other Divines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But I hope ſtill they teach us right.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But it is not enough to ſay you hope, you muſt be ſure the Governours of the Church are in the wrong, or elſe you are in a moſt miſerable condition to run your ſelves into ſo many Sins and dangers by ſeparating from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But my Conſcience tells me I am in the right.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But 'tis not your Conſcience will excuſe you, unleſs you have ſome Command of God to build upon. Now turn your Bible over and over, you will not find any thing in the Scripture againſt any duty required by the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But pray where have you any Command of God for your Common-Prayer and Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are commanded in Scripture to make Prayers and Supplications for all Men,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1.</note> and to ſee that all things be done Decently and in Order, and ſince the Words and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are not determined in Scripture, 'tis better the Governours ſhould conſider and make Rules and Orders, then to leave it to every bodies Fancy, ſo that we have command in Scripture for what we do. But, pray, where have you any command of God for your irreverent Prayers and diſorder in Gods ſervice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Why do you call our Prayers and Service irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent and diſorderly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they are ſo, and cannot be generally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; for when every Preacher is to follow his own
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108859:17"/>heated and Rambling fancy, and every Hearer is leſt to Sit, or Kneel, or Stand, or Lye along; to put on his Hat, or put it off: what can commonly be expected, but irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and diſorder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> As for theſe Modes, Geſtures and Poſtures, which you call Irreverent, we matter not them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But thô you matter them not, yet the Scripture does require all things ſhould be done <hi>Decently and in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> and we find that our Saviour and his Apoſtles did kneel down and ſhew all outward Reverence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we think the Church of <hi>England</hi> has good reaſon to require People to imitate their examples in behaving themſelves Reverently and Orderly when they are in the Houſe of God, and not let their Service be more rude there, then when they are at their houſes at home: ſo that nothing is commanded in this kind, but what civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and good breeding would teach Men to obſerve, and for which we have the command of God, and the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles and other Holy Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Perhaps it would be better if People were more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent at their Meetings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But how can that be expected, when all your Prayers and the whole Performance is left to the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary pleaſure and diſcretion of every Preacher amongſt you, who are Men, and thoſe none of the ableſt neither, and may err and be ignorant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But we think they Pray by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What do you mean by Praying by the Spirit do you mean that the Holy Ghoſt does put all thoſe words immediately into their Mouths, and ſo they uſe no other Prayers, but what are dictated by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> We do think ſo, and our Preachers keep us up in that belief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But how do they prove this? For if that be true, all their Prayers are as Divine and Infallible as the Word of God it ſelf. For the Holy Ghoſt is as Infallible now, as when he did guide the Apoſtles to write the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But it is evident to all the World, that theſe Prayers are often ſo far from being Divine, that they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108859:18"/>ſometimes are ſuch as ſcarce become a ſober Man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may ſee what Men your Preachers are that abuſe you in this manner, and cheat you with falſe ſtories, if your Preachers are dictated by any Spirit, 'tis generally by the Spirit of deluſion; for it is not to be thought, that the Holy Ghoſt will work a Miracle at every Conventicle, to inſpire every diſſenting Preacher, when ordinary gifts are ſufficient not only for ſuch, but much more excellent Prayers: And any One that will but attend thoſe Meetings, and weigh their Prayers with Judgment, will find more of the errour and weakneſs of the Man, then of the leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But we have heard other Men Pray and Preach, but could never find ſo much ſatisfaction and comfort as we do from theſe Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Perhaps their paſſionate way of ſpeaking, their Noiſe, with now and then an affected Sigh and Groan, may ſtir up a preſent paſſion in you, as a good Actor at a Play does, who can make the People cry and laugh when he will; I hope therefore you will not ſay, that the Actor is moved by the Spirit, and thoſe are all made Godly People, that are thus moved and affected as to burſt into Tears; ſo that if you Judge of the ſoundneſs of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by ſuch outward Paſſions, I fear the Player when he ſets about it, will make you believe he is the moſt Sanctified Preacher. Setting then aſide this which is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the working of the Holy Spirit, but an act of the Man, and all the efficacy is loſt in an hour or Two, aſſoon as you come into Company, or are taken up with buſineſs and other affairs: You muſt not therefore Judge of your Religion by a ſudden paſſion, but by your ſound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and ſteady performing all parts of your Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But this cannot be a ſudden Paſſion only in me, but muſt be a real work of the Holy Spirit, becauſe I find a great change in my Life, I am grown more ſober, read and meditate upon Gods Word, and mind Religion more then I did before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But that is no Argament that you are in a ſafe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108859:18"/>way, ſo long as you continue in Schiſm; for when the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil did find he could no longer ruine your Soul by open prophaneſs, he now may tempt you to more ſecret Sins, to more Spiritual wickedneſs, which are as heinous in the ſight of God, and as dangerous to your Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> We have ſatisfied our ſelves all along upon theſe accounts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But you ſee they are weak grounds to rely upon, for all this while thô you are Zealous for ſome, you may be wanting in many other neceſſary duties, and you are guilty of Schiſm, diſobedience to Parents, deſtroy all Diſcipline and Order in the Church, encourage Atheiſm and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs, and endanger the ſafety both of Church and State, meerly upon fancies and humours, for I can call it no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe there is not One good thing that you can learn and obſerve there, that you cannot as well have and practice in the communion of the Church. Beſides you act againſt the Senſe of the Primitive Church, and all other Churches in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If it be ſo, we are much miſtaken, and greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by our Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is certainly ſo, and while you follow ſuch blind and erring guides, no wonder if you fall into deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> We have been told by our Preachers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did verily believe that the Ancient Church were Papiſts, and when the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> did talk to us of following the Doctrine and Government of the Ancient Church, we thought it was only with a deſign to prepare the way to bring us to Popery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now I hope you are ſatisfied that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is no wayes inclining to Popery, but does endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to teach you your Duty according to the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and further to confirm the Truth and ſoundneſs of their interpretation of Gods Word, by the Doctrine of the Primitive Church, and the generall Councils, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Catholick Church. And this you may ſee if you read their late Writings, they do as heartily maintain againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as they did before againſt the other <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108859:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> I am very well ſatisfied now that the Men of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are far from being Papiſts, but you tell me that all other Reformed Churches do approve of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and are ready to joyn with her in communion, and condemn thoſe for Schiſmaticks that ſet up ſeparate Congregations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes I do ſo, and if you will but adviſe with your Biſhops and Miniſters, they will eaſily be able to prove it to your ſatisfaction. You may read much to this purpoſe in my <hi>Evangelical and Catholick unity,</hi> where you have the opinions of <hi>Luther, Melancthon, Bucer</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> in their own words to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Then therein I perceive our Teachers have greatly abuſed us alſo. Indeed I find many rational and ſober Men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and I believe there may be a great deal of Truth in what you ſay, but yet they are of ſuch a perſecuting ſpirit, that they will let no body live quietly by them that are not of their perſwaſion, which we think to be a very ill temper, not becoming the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is a ſad thing that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is the moſt gentle and moderate, and does diſclaim all cruelty and hard uſage upon the account of Religion, ſhould now be accounted the greateſt Perſecutor, as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſhe is at this time. People ſtrangely forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the opinions and practices of their own Party, when they lay ſuch an accuſation upon the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> which does diſown any power of temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But there were many Statutes that did inflict ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere penalties upon Diſſenters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe are made by the State for the ſecurity of the Government; for they finding Diſſenters generally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the publick Peace, and endeavouring changes and alterations by Mutiny and Sedition, ſaw it neceſſary by Penal Laws to reſtrain them from growing too nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and to keep them within the bounds of their duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But does not the Church of <hi>England</hi> then allow of Penal Statutes.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:108859:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In a moderate way ſhe does, to make Men hear and conſider, but not to undoe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſurely Men need not to be uſed like Children, they have diſcretion to mind their duty, without being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up by puniſhments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They ſhould have ſo, but 'tis plain that they have not,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> and therefore God Almighty has placed Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Officers to be a terrour to evil doers, and a praiſe and an honour to them that do well and mind their duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Yes, if puniſhments were inflicted on evil doers, we ſhould like that well; but they puniſh Godly People becauſe they will not go againſt their Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Do you account then all the Idle, Lazy people that lye at home and ſleep, or elſe ſit drinking at Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes in time of Divine Service, and will never ſo much as take pains to underſtand their Catechiſm, and bring their Children to be inſtructed in the Grounds of the Chriſtian Religion, Godly People. Now 'tis evident theſe idle and ignorant People, unleſs they be ſtirred up by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, will never give themſelves the trouble to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and do their duty, and ſo will ruine their own and their Childrens Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If you did puniſh only ſuch idle and lazy. People that did live like Heathens, and require them and their Children to hear and do their duty, no ſober Man but muſt approve of ſuch Diſcipline, and will ſay ſuch People deſerve to be puniſhed. But you puniſh Godly People that do read and meditate upon the holy Scriptures, and take pains to know and do their duty, thô they do not conform to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Laws are made in generall for all that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves from the publick Service, for elſe all idle People would excuſe themſelves under that pretence of being Diſſenters. Beſides many are Diſſenters not out of Conſcience, but out of Pride, Humour, and for temporal advantage; and ſo run into Hereſie, Schiſm, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. It is all the reaſon in the World that ſuch car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections ſhould be reſtrained, and Men obliged to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108859:20"/>hear and conſider the ſober Inſtruction of the Church; and the deſign of all puniſhments is to that purpoſe, that men might not neglect their duty out of humour and lazineſs, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> You will not allow then, that the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> is a perſecuting Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, by no means, no body can with any colour ſay that of Her; ſhe does adviſe all Magiſtrates to uſe that wholeſome Diſcipline which God has appointed, and which all Holy and Religious Magiſtrates have executed, to oblige People to hear and conſider. For as all Parents are bound to teach and correct their Children if they be diſorderly, ſo all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, as they are common Fathers of their Countrey, ought to ſee their Children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the principles of true Religion, and have a right to puniſh their unruly and diſorderly Children: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly there are Laws for that purpoſe, which when executed as they ought to be, bring Peace and Holyneſs to a Nation; thô in the executing them there is great pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and moderation to be uſed, which the Governours are to take into their Conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But why do you ſay the Church of <hi>England</hi> is the moſt moderate Church in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe ſhe like the true Mother, is for correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and not deſtroying her diſorderly Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Surely thoſe that now cry up Toleration, and talk of liberty of Conſcience, when and where they had power, were not for putting to death and exterminating thoſe that did differ from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, you may read lamentable Stories of the cruelty of the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany,</hi> and I need not tell of the cruelties and Murders committed by others, who would be repreſenting the Church of <hi>England</hi> for a perſecuting Church. I ſhall not name particulars, inquire and you will eaſily ſatisfie your ſelves that the Church of <hi>England</hi> does but adviſe ſuch moderate diſcipline, as Fathers ought to exerciſe over their Children, when the Diſſenters are generally not ſatisfied but with blood and deſtruction.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:108859:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> I cannot ſay, but you ſpeak a great deal of reaſon in the defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and I perceive many good Men think it no harm to joyn with her upon occaſion, but they think they may alſo goe and hear a good Sermon in a Meeting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But is not that to ſet up a Schiſm, and plainly to make a fraction in the Church, and it is encouraging Children to think meanly of, and to deſpiſe their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Parents, and Maſters, for what is it but the very caſe that, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi> blames in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that <hi>one was for Paul, another for Apollos, another for Cephas;</hi> for thô a Diſſenter may Preach well, yet when he does it in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Church, without any call, and does draw People into parties, it is that Schiſm which is condemned by the Scripture, and will bring all thoſe miſchiefs that I have already ſpoken of; and does plainly teach Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to deſpiſe their Governours, Miniſters and fellow Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But why do you ſay thoſe Preachers have no call?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe moſt of them have no Ordination, and if they had, they have no Licence and Authority from the Biſhops and Governours; and ſo by the Law of Chriſt, and the conſtant Rule of the Church, they have no power to Preach, for <hi>how ſhall they Preach except they be ſent?</hi> If they were Ordained, they ought not to thruſt themſelves into another Mans charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Thô they have no outward Call from the Church, yet they are ſent by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How do you prove that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Becauſe we find them endned with excellent gifts, and Chriſt did not beſtow ſuch Talents to be hid in a napkin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gifts are no Argument that a Man has a Lawfull call, for a Heretick or a Schiſmatick may have Gifts, and uſe them to divide and deſtroy the Church. Therefore as none muſt Preach without a call, ſo if any that are called turn Heretick or Schiſmatick, he may be ſilenced again, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.10. for beſides gifts, there muſt be a ſober and orderly Converſation, ſound profeſſion, Obedience to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108859:21"/>Orders of the Church; and if this Method were not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and Men tied to be Peaceable and Cuiet, and ſubject to their reſpective Governours, the Church would be the moſt confuſed Society in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> I confeſs Miniſters ought to be quiet and peaceable Men, and they ought to promote Love and Unity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But after this way of running into Conventicles, there can be neither Love nor Unity, nor holineſs in the Church, for one Preacher will be ſetting up in oppoſition to another, and Sects and Diviſions will daily increaſe: And you ſee by experience Schiſmaticks differ one from another, as they do from the Church, and then fall a cenſuring and condemning one another, as much as they did the Church; and thence proceed Hatred, Strife, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Quarrels and Contentions, and Hereſies; Ignorance and Profaneſs overſpread the Nation, and all theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs come upon us, becauſe Men will not ſubmit to that Order and Government that Chriſt has ſet in his Church, but after their own luſts <hi>heap to themſelves Teachers having iſching Ears.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> Now the Scripture ſays, Men that thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Peace and Order of the Church muſt have their mouths ſtopped, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11. But if they are not ſtopped, all good Chriſtians ought to avoid having any thing to do with them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Then I perceive you would take away the liberty of Conſcience granted by the Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Act of Parliament is only to free you from the puniſhment that might be inflicted upon you by Law on your Body or Eſtate, and is equally extended to <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Quakers,</hi> and other Hereticks, and almoſt Perſons of all Perſwaſions whatſoever, and to keep them quiet as to the State under their perverſe humours; and therefore was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meant to lead you to the way of Salvation, or to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them to be good Chriſtians; and my deſign is rightly to inform your Conſcience, and perſwade you not to uſe this liberty for a Cloak of maliciouſneſs: and to take this opportunity to run from the truth, is the way to bring upon your ſelves everlaſting deſtruction, as many do, that forſake the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:108859:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Do you think then we are in ſuch a dangerous condition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not for me to pronounce Sentence upon any One as to the other World; but according to the Rules of Gods Word, and the conſtant Senſe of the Catholick Church in all Ages, and of all particular Churches at this day, for Men to ſet up Altar againſt Altar, and ſeparate from their lawfull Governours without juſt reaſon, is that Schiſm condemned by the Goſpel; and that there is no reaſon to ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I have ſufficiently ſhewed by taking off all the Objections againſt her Communion.<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Baxter's</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology pag. 8. I know how unable the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts were to anſwer the many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Famous <hi>Arth. Hilderſham, J. Paget, W. Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, Brightman John Ball,</hi> and other old <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,</hi> for the lawfulneſs of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with our Pariſh-Churches, in the Sacraments and the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. I was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration (true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called) by conſidering. 1. How contrary it is to the Principle of Chriſtian-love. 2. And how directly and certainly pernicious to the intereſt of the cauſe of Chriſt, and his Church, and of the Souls of Men, and how powerful a means it is to kill that little Love that is left in the World— 4. I was greatly moved in thinking of the State of moſt Churches in the World; if I travelled into <hi>Ahaſſia. Armenia, Ruſſia,</hi> or among the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, I durſt not deny to hold communion with them. When I go to God in Prayer, I dare not go in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate capacity, but as a Member of the Univerſal Church, nor would I part with my ſhare in the Common-Poayers of all the Churches, for all the World— And having peruſed all the Forreign and Ancient Liturgies extant in <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum.</hi> I doubt not but our own is incomparably better then any that is there.</note> And conſider what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays in this Caſe, who does alſo own Biſhops, Liturgies and Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Ceremonies, as ours are, no juſt Cauſe of ſeparating from the Church, <hi>viz. Inſtitut. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have ſet down the Preaching of the Word and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, for the ſigns whereby to know the Church— For where the Preaching of the Gospel is reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently heard, and the Sacraments are not neglected, there for that time is a certain face of a true Church, and 'tis lawfull for no Man, without puniſhment, to deſpiſe her Authority, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject her Admonitions, be refractory againſt her Counſels, or mock at her Corrections, much leſs may he ſeparate from her and break her unity. For our Lord does ſo highly eſteem the Communion of his Church, that he does reckon him for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado and deſertor of Religion, that does obſtinately ſeparate from any Chriſtian Society, that does hold the true Miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments; from whence it does follow, that to depare from the Church, is to deny God and Chriſt: but how much the more ought we to take heed of ſuch a wicked Schiſm; for while we go about as much as in us lyes to deſtroy the Truth of God, we deſerve that God ſhould thunder againſt us with the greateſt force of his Wrath, to break as in pieces.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:108859:22"/>
               <head>If ſome Men of better underſtanding by their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence get to a knowledge of the principal parts of their Duty, yet the generality of People, Children and Servants, will be expoſed to all Ignorance, Errour and Profaneſs.</head>
               <p>IN the conſtitution of the Church, the very Order of the Service, and the ſolemn times ſet apart to bleſs God for the particular diſpenſations of the Goſpel, ſuch as the Incarnation of our Lord, at the Feaſt of <hi>Annunciation,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called our <hi>Lady-day,</hi> his Birth at <hi>Chriſtinas,</hi> and ſo his <hi>Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſconſion,</hi> ſending down the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, the Feaſt of the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> with other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Seaſons, are a ſtanding Catechiſm, and with a little help will eaſily bring even Children to underſtand and remember all parts of their Duty, and for their fuller in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and admonition, the Miniſter is to Catechiſe in the Afternoons, and to teach thoſe that are ignorant of theſe things, and to put all others in mind to think upon and obſerve what they do already underſtand. So that Perſons that live in the Obedience of the Church, muſt be ſtupidly careleſs of themſelves, if they want any thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their edification in Faith and Love, and finally to attain Salvation; and if any generally are ignorant of theſe things, they are ſuch who run away from their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and either through ſloth or faction, would not give themſelves the trouble to hear and receive the ſober advice of their Miniſters, and commands of the Church: Then under the Churches diſcipline, the admonition of the Biſhops, the reproof of their Miniſter, good Neighbours and fellow Chriſtians, did reform many of theſe abuſes, and ſtir up others to a diligent attendance upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service. But now all ſorts of temporal puniſhments are in a manner Suſpended, if you by running into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108859:22"/>teach your Children and Servants, your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Acquaintance, to deſpiſe the Authority of their Biſhops and Miniſters, and all the Spiritual diſcipline of the Church, you will be a means to encourage Ignorance and Profaneſs, and in a ſhort time our People will fall into Atheiſm and Infidelity. For many from your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, taught to contemn the reproofs and cenſures of their Governours, will not only neglect the Communion of the Church, but all ſort of exerciſe of Religion, and ſo turn <hi>Pagans,</hi> if not live altogether like brute Beaſts. Others that have as yet ſome ſparks of the Senſe of Religion in generall left in them, yet running up and down from Place to Place, from one Sect to another, will be far from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that firm and ſetled underſtanding of the Grounds and Principles of Religion, which is neceſſary to keep them ſteady in their Duty, and to bulld them up to an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Heavenly converſation. So that you that withdraw your ſelves from the Communion of your Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> beſides the great Sins of Diſobedience, Schiſm, and contempt of the Church, and the danger you run of Hereſie and damnable errour; you do by your pernicious example expoſe your Children and Servants, and multitudes of your fellow Subjects to Ignorance, Profaneſs, Infidelity, Atheiſm; and ſo inſtead of advancing purer Religion, you will bring the greateſt part to no Religion at all; and theſe things we could in a great meaſure prevent, if you by running into Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and deſpiſing the directions of your Governours, did not give them occaſion, and encourage them to run away from the ſober inſtruction of the Church.</p>
               <p>Let me therefore in the Name of God, (and as I have the generall care and charge of your Souls, and ſhall be ready to give any aſſiſtance and direction you ſtand in need of in your paſſage to Heaven) prevail upon you to take theſe things into your ſerious conſideration. Religion is not a politick Engine to be uſed at pleaſure, only to ſerve Mens turns upon occaſion, and gratine their humour, and keep up the intereſt of a party, but 'tis the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and unchangeable Will of God concerning our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108859:23"/>and therefore muſt in all things be carefully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the Rules of his Holy Word; neither muſt we have an eye only to this or that particular Duty, but have regard to all his Commandments: Now Satan does often appear with ſtrong deluſions like an Angel of light, and his inſtruments do with good words and fair Speeches deceive the hearts of the Simple, and put many cheats and fallacies upon unwarie Souls, to bring them into deſtruction. But there are ſcarce any more weak and manifeſt, then thoſe that you have been hitherto abuſed withall, and many of them now evidently falſe by your own confeſſion, as that we were all <hi>Papiſts,</hi> we did worſhip Stocks and Stones, were only morall Men, without any dependance upon the Grace of God, and the direction of his Holy Spirit. And now theſe ſlanders are fully confuted, they turn to other devices, altogether as groundleſs and unreaſonable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as that 'tis indifferent what manner of Governours Men live under in matters of Religion, ſo they live Holy lives, and that they in ſeparating from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> doe no more then ſhe did in Reforming from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> as if it were the ſame to have a publick Service that they do underſtand, with having a publick Service they do not, to have the uſe of their Bibles or not to have them, to worſhip Images, pray to Saints and Angels, be content with half the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, or not, when our Lord requires the whole. To omit many other errours. And not only our Biſhops and Clergy, but Princes and Parliaments did all agree to Reform theſe abuſes, and ſettle our Church upon the ſure foundations of Truth and Holineſs, according to the Word of God, and conſtant Law and Order of the Catholick Church; and there is not one duty of Piety to God, Charity to your Neighbour, and Obedience to the Catholick Church, but you may better practice in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then in any other Society or Communion. Deal ſeriouſly with your own Souls and Conſciences, What can you learn and practice in any Meeting, that you cannot as well obſerve and be taught in the Church? Will you then merely for Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Humours expoſe your own Souls, your Wifes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108859:23"/>and Children, and the whole Nation to the danger of all Hereſies and Schiſms, and bring ſo great a guilt and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction upon your ſelves and Country? If you are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the evil Lives of ſome of our Members, do you come in and joyn with us, and give them better example, and by your Holy and Orderly converſation ſo ſtrengthen our hands to their ſhame and amendment, that we may all follow Peace and Holineſs in this World, and Reign with Joy and Glory in the World to come; but if you ſtill continue obſtinate in your Separation, conſider how you will acquit your ſelves at the great Day, of the guilt of Schiſm, Contempt of Chriſt and his Miniſters, Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Parents, and from being the ſad occaſion of thoſe Hereſies, Profaneſs and Confuſion that have been brought into the Church of God: and that I do not ſay this as my own opinion only, but that which was the fear and apprehenſion of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the beginning of our Reformation, we may learn from their Words, wherein they did as it were by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, foretell the miſeries which ſince fell upon our Nation, and were chiefly brought upon us by this Sin of Schiſm, and neglect of reſorting to the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All and every Perſon and Perſons inhabiting within this Realm or any other of the Queens Majeſties Dominions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall diligently and faithfully, having no lawfull or reaſonable excuſe to be abſent, endeavour themſelves to reſort to their Pariſh Church or Chappel accuſtomed, or upon reaſonable let thereof, to ſome uſual place, where Common-Prayer and ſuch Service of God ſhall be uſed in ſuch time of let, upon every Sunday or other days Ordained and uſed to be kept as Holy-days, and then and there to abide Orderly and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly during the time of the Common-Prayer, Preachings or other Service of God there to be uſed and miniſtred, upon pain of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment by the cenſures of the Church—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And for the due execution hereof, The Queens moſt excellent Majeſty, the Lords Temporal, and all the Commons in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament now aſſembled, do in Gods Name earneſtly require, and charge all the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops and other Ordinaries, that they ſhall endeavour themſelves to the uttermoſt of their knowledges that the due and true execution hereof may be had throughout their Dioceſes and Charges, as they will anſwer before God for ſuch evils and plagues, wherewith Almighty God may juſtly puniſh his People for neglecting this good and wholeſome Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108859:24"/>
               <p>Thô the mit ward Penalty be ſuſpended, in ſome Caſes, yet the Duty ſtill remains, and the reaſon is the ſame, and we may mind Men of it. But what miſeries and calamities our Nation has ſuffered by the neglect hereof ſince that time, need not be told the Men of this generation, wiſh the hinderers of the due execution of this Law formerly, that are left alive, would in time conſider and repent.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſtſcript to the CLERGY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE great buſineſs of our Lives, as Clergy Men, is ſo to inſtract and Rule our ſeveral Charges, that we may be able to ſay with the great Apoſtle, <hi>I am pure from the Blood of all Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>for I have not ſhunned to declare to you all the whole Councel of God;</hi> that will require a great deal of Care and Diligence, but it is a Duty ought to be performed with our utmoſt endeavour, and ſaw will it be if any ſhould periſh through the Miniſters neglect: 'Tis true the Spiritual power Chriſt has given his Church is little underſtood, and all her Authority is much ſlighted by too many in this Age, and the many Diviſions and Schiſms will the reaſe this diſeſteem; therefore 'tis more neceſſary it ſhould be vigorouſſy aſſerted and maintained, and the dangers and miſchieſs that are like to follow upon it ſhould be diſcovered and laid open, while in ſome meaſure they may be prevented. For thô it may ſeem plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſome, and that there can be no harm now and then to hear a good Sermon at a Conventicle, as well as in the Church; yet in the end it will prove fatall to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to ſay no more, what other evils will follow from ſuch a practice, if once eſpouſed by Men of Intereſt and Quality, as God be thanked commonly as yet it is not. Theſe things I have repreſented to you my Brethren at our Viſitation, and I doubt not but you have often urged the ſame to your ſeveral Charges; but becauſe things Read
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108859:24"/>may be better weighed and conſidered, and I can with the ſame pains inform all as a few; I have ſent theſe Papers, the good effect whereof will in a great meaſure depend upon your further Diſcourſes and Management, in more fully enlarging upon and explaining the ſeveral particulars in your Catechiſing and private diſcourſes, and if you can throughly convince your Pariſhioners, that they ought to forſake all other Meetings, and joyn in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that they are bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence you as Chriſts Officers eſtabliſhed by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as really you are, while you are regularly Conſtituted, and faithfully diſcharge your Places, they will eaſily hearken to you in all other Duties. Many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will read theſe Papers, that will not look into a Church. But the deſign of this Diſcourſe is not only to ſhew them the neceſſity of adhering to the outward, Communion of the Church, but to let them ſee how much Religion in generall, and the publick Peace and quiet of Conference is concerned in it, if they will goe upon good grounds; alſo that either through Ignorance or Errour they are like to looſe the main Principles of the Goſpel. My firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire therefore is, that you would take care in Expounding to your Flook thoſe Articles, Rubricks, and Canons which concern Faith, Hope and Charity, and the eſſential Duties of the Goſpel, and then upon occaſion, not always dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon Matters of Diſcipline, let them know, how uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary theſe things are ſo preſerve the unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, and in righteouſneſs of Life, and be ſure not to neglect thoſe Laws that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Catechizing and Expounding the ſame, for the inſtruction of Old and Young according to their ſeveral Capacities; and I deſire you to conſider what weight this Church has layd upon Catechizing, as well before as ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſee the fundamental Principles ſeriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon the Peoples minds, which you find<note n="*" place="margin">Quilibet ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos plebi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidens quater in anno vel per ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vel per alium ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponat populo vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariter abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juslibet ſubtilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tistextura Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtica, quatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordecem fidei articulos, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem mandata de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogi, duo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta evangelii, viz. geminae charitatis, ſeptem opera miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, ſeptem pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata mortalla cum ſua proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſeptem vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes principales ac—gratiae Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta. Idem. de officio Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chidiacon. cap. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Archid. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Archidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconi— quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens Presbyteros invenerint— ſtatutis tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus populo mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <hi>[haec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia]</hi> praedicaſſe ſen publicaſſe, totiens eos ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guant: &amp; poena canonica caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando ſupplere compellant quae temerè omiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> 
               <hi>Linwood Provincial. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de officio Archipresbyteri, c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And then ſtir them up to ſhew their Faith by their good works, in frequenting the Publick Prayers and Sacraments, and leading Holy Lives anſwerable to their Profeſſion.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108859:25"/>For if they really are, or deſire to be good Chriſtians, and Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they muſt not only rely upon talking, and outward Profeſſion, but ſincerely obſerve the Rules and Orders of the Church, both by themſelves and Families.</p>
            <p>There has been a great outcry made againſt many Pious and Learned Divines, under the Name of High Church-Men, &amp;c. and others have been magnified as more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and moderate Men, but all that I could ſee the Church-Men aimed at was,<note place="margin">Jud. 3.</note> 
               <hi>earneſtly to contend for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> in oppoſition to Inſidels and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and ſo to preſerve the Purity of the Goſpel, and to keep a Decency and Reverence in the worſhip of God: and I appeal to the experience of the Nation, where the Publick Prayers and Sacraments are more devoutly offered up and frequented, and what Congregations ſhew the moſt Religious behaviour in the Church? And ſince 'tis the Goſpel by which we muſt be Judged at the laſt day, there is no other way,<note place="margin">Philip. 1.27.</note> to appear with hope before God, then having <hi>your Converſation as becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> Now all theſe Orders of the Church which are contended for, are only applying the Rules of Gods Word, as may moſt tend to edification, and to direct Men in the particular circumſtances of each Ones Duty, and without ſome ſuch Orders and obſervance of them, I do not ſee how Men can keep up a publick Worſhip of God, without being a Scandal to Infidels and Sober Chriſtians, and why the Ancient Rules and Cuſtoms of the Church ſhould be thought an offence, I cannot underſtand, nor how the taking them away can advance Piety in the Nation.</p>
            <p>Theſe Books I commit to your Hands, and deſire you to lend them about in your ſeveral Pariſhes, and make the beſt uſe of them you can, for the benefit of thoſe that you have any hopes will be the better by them. And put them in mind to read and obſerve the Directions in the former Book.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108859:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
